<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A friend to Cæsar, or, An humble proposition for the more regular, speedy, and easie payment of his Majesties treasure, granted, or to be granted by the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, for the carrying on of his Majesties expences, whether ordinary or extraordinary, both in time of peace and in time of war and also the causes of those many debts which the crown is so heavily clogged with, and sound propositions for the cure thereof / by a person of honour.</title>
            <author>Person of honour.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40484</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R226983</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31360597</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31360597</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110745</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40484)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110745)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1739:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A friend to Cæsar, or, An humble proposition for the more regular, speedy, and easie payment of his Majesties treasure, granted, or to be granted by the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, for the carrying on of his Majesties expences, whether ordinary or extraordinary, both in time of peace and in time of war and also the causes of those many debts which the crown is so heavily clogged with, and sound propositions for the cure thereof / by a person of honour.</title>
                  <author>Person of honour.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 3-28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Harford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 6.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Finance.</term>
               <term>Finance, Public --  Great Britain --  To 1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Appropriations and expenditures.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110745:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110745:1"/>
            <p>A FRIEND TO CAESAR. OR AN HUMBLE PROPOSITION FOR The more regular, ſpeedy, and eaſie Payment of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Treaſure, Granted, or to be Granted by the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, for the carrying on of his Majeſties Expences, whether Ordinary or Extraordinary, both in time of Peace and in time of War.</p>
            <p>AND ALSO The Cauſes of thoſe many Debts which the Crown is ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily Clogged with. And ſound Propoſitions for the Cure thereof.</p>
            <p>By a Perſon of Honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Harford</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the Royal <hi>Exchange,</hi> 1681</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:110745:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110745:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>YOu have here, Reader, preſented to your View, one of the moſt uſeful Books this Age has ſeen. This woody, noiſy Age, fruitful only in baſe, in treacherous, or vain Productions, and therefore ſunk in the Esteem of wiſe and Good Men, has the Honour at laſt of Publiſhing this excellent Book, whoſe Merit is too great to be ſpoke in the narrow Limits I oblige my ſelf to. The worthy Author has ſhewn himſelf in the following Pages to be what the Title calls this Book, <hi>a Friend to</hi> Caeſar. No cunning Gloſer of the Court, no fawning Paraſite, no ſupple inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Flatterer, but ſuch a Friend as generouſly interpoſes to free the Sacred Crown of the Brittiſh Empire from that Ruſt and Tervith that has ſo long obſcured its Lustre. The Title of this Book promiſes no more, than what the Author admirably acquits himſelf of in the following Diſcourſe. He has ſhewn himſelf not only by his excellent Deſign and End to be a true Engliſh-Man, a brave, an honeſt, and a worthy Patriot: but alſo by his admirable Management of it, to be a Wiſe and Great Man, capable of the higheſt Reaſonings, and the beſt Reſolves. A fit and juſt diſpoſure of the publick Treaſure, is a Point ſo neceſſary, and withal ſo nice, that as there is nothing more worthy the enquiry of ſuch whoſe Station and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity fits them for the Service of the State; ſo there is nothing that more requires to be propoſed and ſetled by the ſteadieſt Councels, the greateſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberations, and the Wiſeſt Cautions. You will find, Reader, lively Inſtances of the unhappineſs of diverting the publick Monyes from the Ends to which they were appropriated. And every reflecting Mind will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſcern how Fatal ſuch Miſcarriages may prove: when the Peace of
<pb facs="tcp:110745:3"/>Nations ſhall be a Sacrifice to the by-Ends of private Perſons: or when the Treachery of ſome, or the Neglect of others ſhall hazard the ruine of the general Repoſe, or Wreck of the publick Safety. You will find how hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily the Crown is clogged with Debt. You will find many of the plain and obvious (tho concealed or neglected,) Cauſes. And you will find ſuch ſound Propoſitions of Cure, as nothing leſs (I believe) than the collective Wiſdom of the Nation can alter them to mend them. I perſwade my ſelf that no Man can bring any juſt Objection to the ſolid Reaſonings, to the plain Demonſtrations that this Author uſes: If at leaſt he Read with ſuch an attention of Mind as the Subject requires, and comes but to it with an unprejudiced Judgment.</p>
            <p>I have often thought it a most deplorable thing, that the Splendor of the Imperial Crown of theſe Rich and Flouriſhing Nations, ſhould be ſo long Dark'ned and Eclipſed by ſuch a Cloud of Debts. And I have wondred as oft how it could poſſibly be ſo. So many Wiſe and Faithful Miniſters of State, I thought, could never ſuffer their Masters Treaſure to flow out of the proper Channel, and to be diverted to Ends, unworthy the Glory of the Royal Diadem, or unſuitable to the Honour of their own Fidelity and Loyalty. Howſoever it be, the King is unhappily engaged in very great Streights and Difficulties by the preſſing Burthen of his Debts, and as this excellent Author has well dived into the Cauſes, and diſcovered the Moths and Ruſt that inſenſibly by unminded Stepps ſecretly Cankered and Decay'd the Treaſure: So has he with all Candour offered ſuch Means of Redreſs as he has upon the maturest Reſult of Judgment thought the beſt. The Legiſlative Power of the Nation is certainly the best Judge of this Gentlemans Opinion: and himſelf has with all becoming Humility, and due Submiſſion, wholly laid theſe his Sentiments at the Footstool of that Sacred Power. 'Tis a ſence of Duty that every true Engliſhman muſt alwaies cheriſh in himſelf: and which for my own particular, is one of the only things I can Vallue in my ſelf. God forbid therefore that any thing I ſay in this Preface, ſhould be extended to foreſtal the Judgment of a Parliament: for all whoſe Proceedings as I have alwaies the higheſt Veneration and Deference; So I would by no means be thought to intend this a Cenſure upon them, in caſe their Sentiments prove different from the Authors. No, but on the contrary I profeſs to regulate my little Reaſon by their strength of Wiſdom, and reform the Errours of my Judgment, by the Truth of theirs. The occaſion of my Writing this, was no more than an exceſs of Love and Zeal, I naturally have for my King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, which alwaies taking new Fire at every hint that ſpeaks any brave or generous Service to them, broke out into rapture at the reading of theſe
<pb facs="tcp:110745:3"/>Sheets. My Breaſt I found was too narrow for the Genius that inſpir'd it, and no longer able to contain, at laſt it thus ran on. I could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear recommending a thing I liked ſo well, to the glad peruſal of others: and the Bookſeller would needs publiſh what I writ, I cannot but confeſs't an Honour to me; for by this Advantage ſomething of me may remain to future Ages, whileſt annexed to this inestimable Jewel, and this worthleſs Scribble, which otherwiſe perhaps had periſhed in the next Fire, or which is worſe, bin continued by the fate of <hi>Wilds</hi> and <hi>Flecknots</hi> Workes to caſe up Fruit, might now (had I the vanity to ſubſcribe it) convey my Name and Memory to the utmoſt end of time. I could never end, Reader, did I give but way to all the Violence and Heat that agitates my Mind. What could not be ſaid on this Glorious, this Loyal, this uſeful Theme! A Propoſition for eſtabliſhing and ſecuring a lasting Glory to the Engliſh Crown and Nation, by delivering the Crown from the wretched ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of its Debts, and by Protecting it from all future Invaſions of that kind. This Glorious Deed once done, I ſhould not doubt to ſee in a ſhort time, the Royal Engliſh Lyons rouſe themſelves to the Fear and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of all their inſulting Neighbours. But I will not go too far: nor too long detain the Reader from the uſeful Sheets that follow. I will only beg the Readers Patience, and the Authors Pardon for adding the following Opinion of mine, to what the worthy Author ſpeaks about Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streſs, where the Collectors do not preſently pay in their Mony when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. I conceive that not meerly a Conſtable, but in the Country ſome Juſtices of the Peace, or in a Corporation the Major or other chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate ſhould be preſent at the Distreſs of the Goods, of ſuch as ſhall delay Payment of or any wayes imbezel the publick Monyes, both for the greater ſolemnity of the thing, as being the publick Mony, and to prevent the Odium and Revenge that may attend a particular Perſon for doing it. That I may keep my Word with the Reader and no longer uncharitably detant him from the Book it ſelf, I will but add my hearty Wiſhes and Prayers for the auſpicious Progreſs and Event of this worthy Authors generous Deſign; and again asking his Pardon for thus preſuming, and of the Reader for his Detention, conclude this Preface, and conduct you to the excellent Book it ſelf.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>FAREWEL.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:110745:4"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome new Books, Printed and Sold by <hi>Robert Harford,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil</hi> near the Royal <hi>Exchange, 1681.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Reformed Biſhop: or XIX Articles tendered by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a well wiſher of the preſent Government of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (as it is ſetled by Law) in order to the further eſtabliſhment thereof. <hi>Octavo,</hi> price bound, 2<hi>s.</hi> 6<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Treatiſe of Taxes and Contributions, ſhewing the Nature and Meaſures of Crown-Lands, Aſſeſſments, Cuſtomes, Poll Monys, Lotteries, Benevolence, Penalties, Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polles, Offices, Tythes, raiſing of Coins, Harth-Money, Exciſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With ſeveral interſperſed Diſcourſes, and Digreſſions concerning Wars, the Church, Univerſities, Rents and Purchaſes, Uſury and Exchange, Banks and Lombards, Regiſters for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances. Beggars, Enſurance, Exportation of Money, Wool, Free Ports, Coins, Houſing, Liberty of Conſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſame being frequently applyed to the State and Affaires of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and is now thought ſeaſonable for the preſent Affairs of <hi>England. Quarto,</hi> price ſtitched <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Humane Prudence, or the Act by which a Man may raiſe himſelf and Fortune to Grandeur, by A. B. <hi>Twelves,</hi> price bound 1<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Count of <hi>Gabalis,</hi> or Conferences about ſecret Sciences, rendered out of French into Engliſh, with an Advice to the Reader, by <hi>A. L. A. M. Twelv.</hi> price bound, 1<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Jeſuits Catechiſme, according to St. <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> for the Inſtructing and Strengthning of all thoſe that are weak in that Faith. Wherein the Jmpiety of their Principles, Perniciouſneſs of their Doctrines, and Iniquity of their Practices are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. <hi>Quarto,</hi> price ſt. 1<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Politician Diſcovered, or Conſiderations of the late Pretenſions that <hi>France</hi> Claims to <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and her Deſigns and Plots in order thereunto, in two ſerious Diſcourſes, by a true Proteſtant, and well-wiſher of his Country. <hi>Qu.</hi> pr. ſt. 6<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Mathematical Compendium, or uſeful Practices in Arithmetick, Geometry, and Aſtronomy, Geography and Navigation, Embattelling, and Quartering of Armies, Fortification and Gunnery, Gauging and Dyalling, explaining the Logarithms, with new Indices; <hi>Nepairs</hi> Rods or Bones; making of Movements, and the Applications of Pendulums; with the Projection of the Sphere for an Univerſal Dyal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By Sr. <hi>Jonas More</hi> Knight, late Surveyor General of his Majeſties Ordnance. The ſecond Edition with large Editions. <hi>Twelves,</hi> price bound 3<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Church Papiſt (ſo called:) his Religion and Tenets fully diſcovered, in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Diſpute, which long ſince happened between a (then) reputed Papiſt, and an open profeſſed Romaniſt, whereby the common (and trite) Arguments of pretended Viſibility, Succeſſion, Vinverſality, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Roman Church, travelling the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to amuſe and ſtagger the Weak, and to ſeduce and pervert the unſtable ſort of People, are briefly Confuted. Whereunto is added, a ſhort Diſcourſe, proving E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy to be of Divine Inſtitution, Kingly Government of Gods ſetting up, and the Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to be the beſt in the World. By one of the Children of the late Captivity, <hi>Quarto,</hi> price 6<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>All the Letters, Memorials, and Conſiderations, concerning the offered Alliance of the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> to the High and Mighty Lords, the States of the united Neatherlands, according to the ſeveral times when they were delivered: With Conſiderations on the Alliance, and alſo Reflections on the ſaid Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Faithfully Tranſlated from the Dutch Coppies Printed at <hi>Haerler</hi> by <hi>Barent Janſen, Hoog Euys,</hi> 1680. <hi>Folio,</hi> price 6<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Priviledges and Practice of Parliaments in <hi>England,</hi> Collected out of the Common Laws of this Land. Seen and allowed by the Learned in the Laws. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the high Court of Parliament. <hi>Quarto.</hi> ſt. 6<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The great Preſſures and Grievances of the Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> and their Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy to the late Ordinances made againſt them; both out of the Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> and ſeveral other Fundamental Laws of <hi>France;</hi> and that theſe new Illegalities, and their Miſeries are contrived by the Popiſh Biſhops Arbitrary Power, Gathered and Digeſted by E. E. of <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> ſometimes under-Secretary to the French King. Humbly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to his Majeſty of Great <hi>Brittain</hi> in Parliament.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:110745:4"/>
            <head>A FRIEND TO CAESAR, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT appears by ſeveral Acts of Parliament, that the Nation hath frequently been charged with great Sums of Mony, for the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Wars, and for other the neceſſary Service of the Crown and Nation.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Sums for Methods ſake were by their ſeveral Acts di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed to the reſpective Counties, and Cities of the Nation, and afterwards ſubdivided by Commiſſioners appointed by the ſame Acts into Hundreds, Wapes, and Wapentakes in each County, and the whole Sum for one or three Months laid upon every diſtinct County apportioned to the reſpective Hundreds thereof, and the Proportion allotted to every Hundred, ſubdivided again by the Commiſſioners of each Hundred, into ſo many Parts as there are Diviſions in that Hundred, more or leſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the greatneſs and ſmallneſs of the Diviſions, and Warrants Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued out by the ſaid Commiſſioners, to the Conſtables of each Diviſion, to Collect the Sum required after an Aſſeſſment thereof made by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, or ſome of them, appointed thereunto by the Commiſſioners of each Hundred.</p>
            <p>This Money, laid uppon each Diviſion of each Hundred, is again ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided into Pariſhes, and thoſe Pariſhes into the reſpective Townſhips of each Pariſh, and at length ſtated by the Aſſeſſors, upon each indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual Inhabitant of each Townſhip, that hath any Eſtate Real or Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, to render him or them lyable to pay any part of what is laid upon that Diviſion; And ſo the whole Treaſure granted by the Acts (or ought to be) collected and paid by the Inhabitants of every Townſhip, by all Townſhips in every Pariſh, by all Pariſhes in every Diviſion, by all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in every Hundred, by all Hundreds in every County, and by all Counties in the whole Kingdom. A way very ſuitable to the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the repreſentative of the People, and much becoming the Juſtice of the High Court of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:110745:5"/>Yet if I may have Leave, without Offence, I would humbly demand,</p>
            <p>How it comes to paſs, that notwithſtanding ſo Many, ſo Great and Unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd Sums of Money as have been given and granted to his Majeſty, ſince his happy return to his Crown, His Majeſty ſhould yet be ſaid not only to have an Empty Exchequer, but alſo to be much in debt to ſeveral of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>In all Diſeaſes of the Body Natural, we ſay to diſcover the Cauſe of the Diſtemper, is half a Cure, and to remove it, will totally reſtore the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. What is true in the Diſtemper of the Body Natural, is as equally true in the Diſtemper of the Body Politick; take away the Cauſe, and the Effect ceaſeth. And however it is not eaſy (yea 'tis impoſſible) to Aſſign all the grounds and cauſes of his Majeſties unhappineſs in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, after the expreſſion of ſo much Love, Loyalty, and Affection from his Parliament and People, who almoſt (if not altogether) have at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Seſſion, given him for theſe ten Years paſt, little or much to enable him to carry on his Affairs, without expoſing himſelf to Debts, and other griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſadvantages to himſelf and his People, yet ſome of them that are too obvious (and the grand Cauſes among many others) ſhall be given in anſwer to this Inquiry, for the future prevention of ſo great a diſſervice, both to his Majeſty and his People, who by reaſon thereof is alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, and yet hath not ſufficient, and who are always giving, and yet are as far from their end in giving, as if they had given little or nothing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Reaſon or Cauſe that I ſhall mention may be in the Parliaments not giving or granting, what they do give or grant, till the Service for which it is given, be commenced or in ſome forwardneſs for its Expence, whereby his Majeſty is oftentimes forced either to advance his Treaſure up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Credit of what they are about to give him, or for want thereof to purchace all or moſt Commodities requiſite for his Service, at exorbitant Rates and Prizes, which renders it much more in Charge and Expence, than otherwiſe it would or ought to be.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe Allowances given by the Parliament out of the Treaſure, given his Majeſty in their reſpective Acts to ſeveral Perſons, though in it ſelf, it be upon view, but of ſmall or no conſideration; to wit; one penny or two pence in the Pound, Yet if theſe pence or two pences be caſt up, and put into a total Sum, to be defaulked from the whole Sum given, it will then appear that the want thereof is a great Detriment to his Majeſty, and doth fruſtrate his Service (as to ſo much) beyond his expectation from the Sum given him. As for Example, ſuppoſe the Sum given to be two Millions (as of late it hath been and more) four pence in the Pound, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed into pence and two pences to ſeveral perſons, amounts in the whole, Two Millions to 33333 <hi>l.</hi> 06 <hi>s.</hi> 08 <hi>p.</hi> This 33333 <hi>l.</hi> 06 <hi>s.</hi> 08 <hi>p.</hi> if duly paid would anſwer his Majeſties expectation of two Millions of Treaſure ſaid to be given his Majeſty, and the Parliaments intention in giving him ſo much, whereas this defaulkation in the Act it ſelf, renders the Sum ſo much leſs than is promiſed, and his Majeſty ſo much the more in debt for want of it, and the Subject liable to future Taxations for the ſame Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, which he hath already paid as part of the two Millions formerly granted.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:110745:5"/>3. The Anticipation of his Majeſties Revenues, by Loanes from the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of London, and other private Men or Places (before what is given him by his Parliament is or can be reckoned,) is a great cauſe of its expence, without that Providence which otherwiſe might be uſed, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of leaving his Majeſty under the burthen of debt, as much (if not more) than he was before it was given him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The paying of Intereſt to all Venders of Goods or Commodities ſerved into the Navy, for the carrying on his Majeſties Service there, is intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerably diſadvantagious to his Majeſty, and contracts upon him ſuch, and ſo great Debts, that unleſs the Parliament be conſtantly giving, his Majeſty muſt needs ſink under the weight of them (for over and above the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and bare Intereſt allowed) theſe men knowing before-hand, what courſe they muſt ſteer, before they can compaſs their Money, will not part with their reſpective Commodities, without the incluſion of 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> Profit for their Goods ſold, for which upon receipt of Bills or Deben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for their Money, they immedlately carry them to the Exchequer, and enter them there as ſo much Money lent to his Majeſty, at 7 or 8 <hi>per Cent.</hi> till they be paid, whereby it appears to me (I know not what it doth to other men) that his Majeſty loſeth 30 <hi>per Cent.</hi> of all Bills or Debentures ſo brought into his Exchequer, as Money lent for Goods ſold into the Service, which muſt needs leave his Majeſty as much in Debt at the end of the Year as he was at firſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Payment of thoſe Moneys either lent or anticipated by Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes, or brought into the Exchequer by Bills or Debentures in the new way, commonly called by COURSE, is the Ivy that eats out the Heart of his Majeſties Revenue; for though it be true that the Parliament have in their Wiſdoms, made ſtrict <hi>Proviſoes</hi> in ſeveral Acts, for the due pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, without much Charge or Fees to the Vender or Buyer, yet it is alſo true that, let them do what they can to prevent the Miſchiefs that may attend their Payment Irregularly or out of Courſe, yet (when they have done all) all that they have done, nor doth nor can ſignify any thing as to the freeing his Majeſty from being in Debt, in regard what they build upon in this way, is that which cannot ſtand for want of a ſure and ſolid Foundation to bear it upon.</p>
            <p>For whatever is or may be pretended unto by thoſe Gentlemen that were the firſt contrivers of this way, as men intereſted to promote it, yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the way it ſelf is a Sandy Foundation, and ſo far from anſwering its end, to wit, the ſpeedy payment of his Majeſties Debts, that it is totally deſtructive to him and the Nation, and the longer it is followed, the more he will find himſelf plunged into Debt; So that if he had not the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Purſes and Affections to ſupply him in a conſtant way of giving, he would never be able to extricate himſelf out of them. And to ſpeak plainly, Payments in courſe, are at the beſt but coarſe Payments, both in reference to his Majeſties Honour and Profit, and with reference to his Peoples ſatisfaction, except ſuch as are interreſſed Perſons, or uſurious Abuſers of his Majeſties Service. I ſhall take leave to expatiate a little upon this Head, becauſe I know it to be the greateſt <hi>Diana</hi> of theſe times, and is looked upon as the rareſt Expedient that ever was found out for the Honour of his Majeſties Service.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe a Lord, or other Noble Man of this Nation, whoſe Revenue
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110745:6"/>is 5000 Pound good Eſtate, to be alſo an adventurer to the Eaſt Indies, or Guinny, twenty thouſand Pounds with hopes and deſign to improve his Fortune, who yet by reaſon thereof and other Expences, incumbent upon him for the ſupport of his Family, and maintenance of himſelf in that grandeur, that his Birth, Office at Court, or Nobility requireth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets himſelf unwarily into Debt to ſeveral men 40000 <hi>l,</hi> which if paid, would almoſt ruine his Eſtate, and if not paid will grow more and more upon him every Year. Suppoſe alſo this Nobl-eMan, upon conſideration of his preſent condition, ſhould adviſe with his Steward or other Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants or Friends, what courſe to take to free himſelf from this great preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Debt: It cannot be imagined that any faithful Steward or Friend will ſay, Sr. you have 5000 Pounds <hi>per Annum</hi> in good Revenue, ſettle it upon your Creditors for their ſecurity, that their Debts ſhall be paid them, but limit your ſelf to no time when, only ingage your Income for the Principal, and pay them Intereſt, till you can pay them both Intereſt and Principal, and that they may be ſatisfied that you intend really and truly to pay them one time or other; give them order that all and every of them ſhall bring his and their Bills, Bonds, Book-Debts or what elſe ſoever he hath to ſhew for his Debt to your Steward, and there enter their Claim upon Record with Promiſe, that he that comes firſt ſhall be firſt paid, and he that comes laſt, muſt be content to ſtay till the laſt but himſelf be paid, only both the firſt and laſt ſhall all be aſſured that let the Payment be when it will (ever or never) they ſhall all be paid in Courſe, and they ſhall all have Intereſt allowed them till it be paid, though never, or never ſo late firſt.</p>
            <p>Yet admit he or they ſhould thus adviſe this Noble-Man, can any rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Man think that this is a good way or propoſition to diſingage him from his Debts, or that it is a good Foundation laid to free him from them, and yet preſerve his Eſtate, Honour, Adventure and all neceſſary Expences in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire? ſurely no; Conſidering that by this Advice his Revenue muſt be pawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Creditours, his Adventure will daily call upon him for more Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues, his Honour will require that he ſhould ſtill live at the ſame rate as formerly, and that the Intereſt of his 40000 Pounds Debt will be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant eating Charge upon his Eſtate. Muſt not theſe Incumbrances needs leave him in a worſe Condition as to his Debts the next, than he was this Year, if he reſolves to take up or proſecute this Way or Advice.</p>
            <p>For the Intereſt of 40000 Pound for one Year is 2400 Pound, which is almoſt half as much as his whole Revenue can drown of his Debts for that Year, ſo that he pays but 2600 Pounds of his 40000 Pound Debt in one whole Year, and is left at loſs how to equip and ſet to Sea his Ships the next Year, having all his Revenue in Lavender to his Creditours. If he doth not ſet them forth, he hazards the loſs of his 20000 <hi>l</hi> Stock, if he doth, he muſt then advance Money upon the Credit of his whole Eſtate to do it withal, and this involves him into a greater Debt than he was in at firſt. If he cannot take up Money without great Diſadvantage, then there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left him but to hire his Ships, Man, Victual, and Store them with all Commodities fit for the Trade he drives, upon Truſt or Ticket from ſuch as will truſt him or ſell their Commodities to him at 6, 6, and 6 Months time, till his Ships return from Sea, at what time he hath Freight, Victual and Wages to pay to all his Seamen and Owners as a growing Debt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. Now I pray conſider will any of thoſe that truſt him with their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110745:6"/>Goods at ſuch Days of Payment (if they know his Condition) not include in the Price of their Goods, ſo much Profit as may bear the hazard and adventure of their Truſt and Forbearance? ſurely they will. And by how much his Neceſſity may pinch him to make uſe of their Courteſie, by ſo much he may aſſure himſelf they will grow upon him in the Price, and Profit of their Commodities, and this runs him more and farther into debt than ever; for he that drives a Trade upon Ticket or Truſt, either by advanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Money at Intereſt, or taking up Goods at Time, is and muſt needs be in a ſad Condition as to his Trade.</p>
            <p>Unto which we may alſo add that if this Lord or Noble-Man ſhall yet reſolve to live at as high a rate as ever for the Maintenance of himſelf, his Lady and Family, and for the upholding his Reputation in Court and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try (Neceſſity being laid upon him ſo to do,) then certainly his Debt muſt and will increaſe upon him every Year, ſo long as he continues in this courſe, and ſink him deeper and deeper into Debt, and all this (and more that might be ſaid) upon the ſingle Accompt of this Sandy Foundation or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice given him by his Steward to enable him to creep out of Debt by degrees.</p>
            <p>I liſt not to make any Application of this Parallel to the Caſe in hand, an eaſie underſtanding will ſave me that labour, and though I know that Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies do not run upon four Feet, yet I ſhall take the boldneſs to tell my Reader, that as this Courſe is and muſt be greatly deſtructive and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the private Eſtate, Honour and Reputation of this Lord or Noble-Man, ſo it is infinitely much more in the caſe of the King, in regard no Compariſon between a private Man and a Prince, will or can reach the ſad Loſs and Dammage that muſt and will attend his Service, more than any private Mans whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The next begetter of his Majeſties great Debts, is the non-payment of the Seamens Wages ſo ſoon as the reſpective Ships come into Harbour, and are ſafe at their Moarings after the Service is ended, the neglect or want whereof is the Ground and Cauſe of that devouring Charge that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends his Majeſties Service.</p>
            <p>What the Dammage thereof is or may be, is not eaſily diſcerned by moſt Men, and little conſidered by thoſe that do diſcern it, as being neither their Horſe nor their Load; but that you may ſee a little into the miſchief thereof, I ſhall crave Leave to hold it forth in the Example of a Ship of 200 Men, that by the Foot you may better gueſs at the Body of great Sea-Monſters.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe a Ship manned with 200 Men, and employed in his Majeſties Service for ſix Months paſt, to come into Harbour, and for want of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to pay off, the Company lyes at her Moarings, or in dry Dock one Month, full manned in Victuals and Wages; the Queſtion before us is, what Dammage this is to his Majeſty for the growing Debt of Victuals and Wages for that Month.</p>
            <p>That we may the better ſee the Dammage, we muſt inquire and know what is the Debt from his Majeſty for the whole Company for their ſix Months Service paſt. Now the Debt for the Wages of 200 Men for one Month, (ſuppoſed at 30 Shillings <hi>Medium</hi> for one Man) comes to 300 Pounds, which for ſix Months is 1800 Pounds. This being ſtated, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that the Dammage his Majeſty ſuſtains for the want of 1800 Pounds
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110745:7"/>to pay off theſe 200 men is for one Months Wages 300 Pounds, unto which if you add for the Price of their Victuals for the ſame Month (at 20 Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings <hi>medium</hi>) it amounts to 200 Pounds more, and is in the whole 500 Pounds, which is 200 Pounds more than one quarter part of the whole 1800 Pound Debt for ſix Months. Now how unreaſonable a thing is it that his Majeſty ſhould for want of 1800 Pound preſent Money be ſmitten into Debt 500 Pound in one Month, and ſo in proportion into a greater or ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Debt, for a longer or ſhorter time, whileſt the ſaid Ship lies unpaid? If the preceding Article of Anticipation be by the bare Intereſt of Money, ſuch a loſs to his Majeſty, what Detriment is this at ſuch a time when yet his Majeſty hath no need of, nor Service for thoſe men whom he both feeds and payes?</p>
            <p>Let thoſe that can, caſt it, for my part, though I can I will not, as aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſay what it is; and upon that account I muſt confeſs that I have ſometimes ſtood amazed to think upon the Improvidence (I muſt not ſay Imprudence) of ſome employed in his Majeſties Service, that ſhould take care to prevent this Miſchief, not much inferiour to the laſt mentioned; And I dare affirm that and if it be no better provided againſt in the future, than it hath been for time paſt, let the Parliament give what Treaſure they pleaſe to his Majeſty, to carry on his Service in time of War; this very particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſhall ſwallow up a great part thereof, and leave his Majeſty more in Debt at the end of every Voyage or Service, than can be recovered or paid without new Supplies from the Nation, for if 200 Men ſhall beget him 500 Pound in Debt for one Month, it is not difficult to ſay what the whole or great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of a Fleet manned with 30 or 40000 Men ſhall fleece from him for two or three Months together.</p>
            <p>It would be accounted an officious Act to diſcover what Debts his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty contracted in this particular, for and during the late War with the <hi>Dutch.</hi> And though it be not difficult to Collect it by the reſpective Sea Books of each Ship in the Fleets then ſet to Sea (diſcompting the time from each Ships coming to her Moarings, till the day ſhe was paid off) yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is better to be concealed than made publick, for if it were exactly caſt up and known, it would aſtoniſh his Majeſty to think how his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure hath been waſted, and his Debt increaſed without any Service done for it, being paid not ſo much for Wages earned, as Money caſt away for want of Treaſure to pay what they had already earned, before they came to their Moarings.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Among other Cauſes of his Majeſties contracting great Debts upon him, it is none of the leaſt to farm out his ſetled Revenues; Such as the Excize of Beer and Ale, Chimney-Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſuch men as will contract for them, for this is the way to render theſe Collections one third part leſs than indeed they are, and conſequently his Majeſty ſo much the more in Debt. It cannot be denyed but that all Undertakers or Farmers of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Revenues, Fiſh for Profit to themſelves, and were they not aſſured that in probability they might gain to themſelves one third Part more than what they engaged to pay, they would never oblige themſelves and their Eſtates to make good what they promiſe. We may add to this that all Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance-Money upon the Contract or Farme taken, leſſens the Revenue ſo much the more, by how much the more ready Money they do advance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they enter upon their Contract, for it is not to be believed that theſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110745:7"/>men would depoſite ſo great Sums as they do, were it not as a Shooing-horn, the better and eaſier to draw the Contract (as a Shooe) on their Feet. And though here be no viſible Loſs of Intereſt Money to his Majeſty by this Anticipation, as in the caſe of other Loanes (yea rather a ſeeming viſible Profit,) yet the inviſible Loſs included in the Contract it ſelf, is more than the Profit of double Intereſt to the Farmer, and conſequently more than the Loſs of double Intereſt to his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Nor muſt I omit (though I know it a Digreſſion from the Point in hand) that great reflection upon his Majeſties Honour that attends this way of Farming, for under pretence of his Majeſties Grant or Commiſſion, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Farmers skrew and tenter the Subject unto or beyond the Letter or Meaning of the Act of Parliament, yea contrary to Certificates produced from the Juſtices of the Peace, that they are free'd from Payments by the Act it ſelf, and thereby they render their Lives bitter to them, and their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates exceeding Poor and Low. Hence comes Clamour, Diſcontentedneſs againſt the preſent Government, and the Cry of the Poor againſt their own Truſtees. I know that moſt of theſe Undertakers are Gentlemen of Quality in their reſpective Countries, where their Farm lies (though ſome alſo are Strangers to the Places, and live far remote) but I know withal that theſe Gentlemen do not Act in their own Perſons, farther than to regulate or methodize their Profit upon the whole Farm, and when that is done, they let out their Farms to Subcontractors, if they can get any that will come up to their Price, ſo as to aſcertain their deſigned Profit, and if they cannot ſo do, then they depute the Power of his Majeſties grant to them, to Subcollectors for their Uſes, who generally are men of ſmall (if any) Reputation in the Countries or Places where they live, and who for the moſt part do employ ſuch men under them as are much inferiour to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and altogether unfit to receive any Truſt. And theſe are the men that rake and tear, that grieve and vex the Subject, which the firſt undertakers and ſometimes their Subcontractors and Subcollectors are aſhamed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in, though yet it be connived at both by the one and the other, to be done by theſe inferiour Inſtruments, in order to the improvement of their Farm or Contract, the Profit whereof was the firſt Bait that inticed them to bite at his Majeſties Service, whatever might otherwiſe be pretended.</p>
            <p>Thus I have endeavoured to give you a few of the many Grounds and Cauſes of his Majeſties paſt and preſent great Debts, notwithſtanding all that large and liberal Aid he hath and doth receive from his Subjects, by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Acts of Parliament.</p>
            <p>I could eaſily enlarge, and both tire my ſelf, and my Reader in ſpecify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many more, which though happily they are or may not be ſuch, and ſo great as thoſe before mentioned, yet of themſelves they are of great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, and highly prejudicial to his Majeſties Service, by licking up (beyond all Bounds and Reaſon) his Majeſties Treaſure, and hurrying him into Debt as I may ſay, over Shooes and Boots. Such are the Management of his Naval Affairs in the Victualling Office by Contract, too great Salle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to ſubordinate Inſtruments, want of ſeaſonable Supplies of the Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeens in all his Majeſties Yards and Store-Houſes, buying all ſorts of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions at extream Rates and Prizes when (and not before) Neceſſity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth their ſupply, payment of thoſe Proviſions in a long bow of time, furn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhing the neceſſity of one Yard or Store-Houſe with the Proviſions of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110745:8"/>Yard after they are laid in there, at exorbitant Rates and Charge, want of due Muſters, and in Default thereof Payment, of dead Payes to Captains, Purſers, <hi/> Imbezellments of Boteſwaines, Gunners, and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, the abuſe of provant Cloaths ſold to Seamen preſt into the Service, buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poor Seamens Tickets, compounding for Bills and Debentures, when there is Money in the Office to pay them, Diverting his Majeſties Treaſure to private Uſes. Theſe and an hundred more, that with an eaſie Recollecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might be ennumerated, are all tending much to the Diſſervice of his Majeſty, the contracting of greater Debts than needs, the Diſcouragement of the Subject to ſerve his Majeſty with Proviſions, the Diſcontent of the whole Nation, and the Diſappointment of the good Intentions of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in laying ſo many and ſo great Burthens and Taxes upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, with deſign to preſerve his Majeſty from being in Debt. But in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, all or the moſt part of theſe (and thoſe I paſs over with Silence) are ſuch as are already in the Hands and Care of Subordinate Inſtruments, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with their Regulation and Prevention, I ſhall rather chooſe in Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to bury them, than by raking in them, to uncover the Nakedneſs of thoſe whoſe Truſt is to reform them. And ſhall proceed in what remains before me, as the Deſign of this whole Diſcourſe, to wit (if it be poſſible) to propound ſuch Expedients as (at leaſt in my poor and weak Capacity) may have a Tendency to preſerve his Majeſties Honour, and to redeem him from thoſe needleſs growing Debts that now burthen him, and in him the whole Nation. And yet to carry on his Majeſties Revenue, Service, and Expence, at as high a Rate of Honour and Value as now it is or can be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be, by all thoſe Contrivances and Practices before mentioned.</p>
            <p>The whole Charge and Expence of his Majeſty may for Methods Sake be looked upon under the Notion of Ordinary or Extraordinary.</p>
            <p>I call ſuch Ordinary as refer to his Perſon, his Houſe, Guards, Buildings, Reparations, Privy-Purſe, Intelligences, Negotiations with forraign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Maintenance of his Navy in Harbour, his Garriſons, Fortifications, Building and Repairing of Ships, together with all other things, that are conſtant Charges upon him, and muſt be kept and maintained by him, and his Succeſſors, as Kings of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I call nothing Extraordinary, but open and Proclaimed War, with one or more Forraign Nations, or Aſſociation with Forraign Princes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is and muſt be forced to raiſe an Army, or ſet out Fleets of Ships to Sea, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For the Common Defence of the Nation, preſervation of Peace, Trade, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe is already provided for and ſetled, the Parliament ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given his Majeſty twelve hundred thouſand Pounds a Year, to enable him to pay and bear all Charges and Expences that may or do attend ſuch things as are of a conſtant being; and muſt of Neceſſity be kept up and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for the preſervation of the Nation in time of Peace, and the Honour of his Majeſties Perſon and Court. And I could heartily wiſh that if what is already ſetled upon him ſhall by experience be found too little, more might be added rather than his Majeſty be expoſed to follow the by-Ways, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of Byaſſed Men, to advance Money for his Neceſſity, and thereby run himſelf into great Debts, not ſo eaſily Diſcharged as Made. It is a ſad Story that the whole Nation of England (I might ſay three whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) ſhould not be ſufficient for the Maintenance of one Man, according
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110745:8"/>to the Nobleneſs of his Birth, the Dignity of his Office, and the Neceſſary Expences that attend it, without ſuch Precarious ways before mentioned, that render him (as a borrower) a Servant to the Lender, and yet after all leavs him in a worſe Condition than he was at firſt.</p>
            <p>The laſt of theſe muſt be provided for, by Additional and Extraordinary Levyes upon the Nation, according to the Greatneſs, and Formidableneſs of the Enemy, the length of the War, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As it ſhall be made known by his Majeſty to his Parliament, who are bound ſeaſonably and ſpeedily to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply what they in their Wiſdoms find fitting, for the better carrying on of the War, both by Sea and by Land, for the Preſervation of his Majeſty, and the Honour and Safety of the Nation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now ſuppoſing the firſt already ſetled, and the laſt to be ſetled by the Parliament: the next Enquiry is how his Majeſty may have and enjoy the full proceed of his Revenue already ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon him for all ordinary Expences, without Snips, Abatements, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulkations or other great Loſs or Dammage before it be collected, or after it is Collected before it is paid to him, or to his uſe, to ſuch Perſons as he ſhall Authorize to receive the ſame. And how his Parliament may for the future ſo ſettle a Reveliue upon his Majeſty, for all extraordinary Charges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in caſe of War, and diſpoſe the Collection, Receipt, Payment, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence thereof, and of every part thereof, that the Nation may not be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, his Majeſty Diſhonoured, nor his Service Retarded, either for want of Treaſure ſufficient to bear the Charge, or want of Care and Fidelity, in the Payment of all Expences the War may require.</p>
            <p>I put the Collection and Payment of all Treaſure, whether for Ordinary Charges in time of Peace, or Extraordinary Expences in time of War to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, becauſe the ſame way to be propounded for the Collection and Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all Treaſure given or to be given his Majeſty for ordinary Expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces is (or with little Variation may be) the way and meaſure of all Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for extraordinary Expences in time of War. For the Collection where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I ſhall humbly Offer to Conſideration theſe enſuing Propoſitions <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That all Acts of Parliament already made, whereby his Majeſty hath any Revenue from the Nation in General, ſuch as Excize upon Ale and Beer, Hearth-Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all future Acts to be made to Levy Money upon the general Body or Bulk of the Nation, for any Cauſe or Cauſes whatſoever, either Ordinary or Extraordinary, be declared by the Parliament to be Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected in manner and form following. That is to ſay, Firſt by every Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the whole Nation, according to the reſpective Proportions aſſeſſed upon them. Secondly, by every Pariſh containing ſuch and ſo many Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips in that Pariſh. Thirdly, by every Diviſion containing ſo many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes in that Diviſion. Fourthly, by every Hundred containing ſo many Diviſions as are in that Hundred. Fifthly, by every County containing ſo many Hundreds as are in that County. And laſtly by the whole Nation, containing ſo many Counties as are in it. As for Cities and other Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Places, the way of Collection may be carried by Pariſhes in that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Corporation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the reſpective Revenues that may ariſe from each Pariſh. This is already practiſed as to all Land Taxes, and needs no Alteration or Amendment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, That two able and ſufficient Men Inhabitants of each Townſhip, be required by the Deputy Lieutenants, Juſtices of the Peace, or other Commiſſioners to Aſſeſs themſelves and the reſt of the Inhabitants
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110745:9"/>of each Townſhip, Pariſh or Diviſion, in every Hundred, and enable to Collect what is ſo by them Aſſeſſed, proportionably to the whole Sum laid upon that Hundred or Diviſion, and thoſe Pariſhes and Townſhips within the ſame. This alſo is the Method of former Times, as to all Land-Taxes, and cannot be put in a better way.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, That this Money or Treaſure, thus Collected, may remain, and be in all and every part thereof, in the Hands of the ſaid Collectors, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, for and till ſuch time as it be required from them by ſuch Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers as ſhall be Impowred to receive and pay, or Aſſign it to be received and paid to ſuch Men to whom the ſame or any part thereof ſhall appear to be due from his Majeſty upon any accompt whatſoever, according to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Truſt of the ſaid Treaſurers, and the due and ordinary Form of that Place and Office, wherein they are Intruſted as Treaſurers, and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, whether they be Treaſurers at War, or for the Army, the Navy, the Houſhold or any other Treaſurers whatſoever, legally warranted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and pay his Majeſties Treaſure and Debts.</p>
            <p>More than this needs not be ſaid or done, with Reference to the Colect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all Aids whatſoever in all Townſhips, Pariſhes, Diviſions, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds and Counties of the whole Nation. And more than theſe, two able and ſufficient Men, are needful to be appointed as Collectors thereof, in their reſpective Townſhips, who are beſt able to know and Determine how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chimnies are in each Houſe of that Townſhip, and how many Ale-Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or Brewers and Drawers of Ale and Beer, do inhabit therein, having the Acts of Parliament to direct them what to do for the one, and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors from the Juſtices or other Commiſſioners for the Hundred, what to Impoſe upon the other, either by the Strike of Mault ſpent, or by the Barrel of Ale drawn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this way propounded his Majeſty ſhall be ſure to have his full Revenue Collected, and depoſited in good Hands ready to be paid to ſuch as by his Authority, ſhall Aſſign the ſame or any part thereof, to all or any of his Creditors, to whom they ſhall give their Aſſignations free of all Charge to his Majeſty, not only for Collecting, but alſo for paying of the ſame. For they do not more, nor ſo much as the Collectors for the Poor, or the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens of every Pariſh, do or ought to do. And by this way it will eaſily appear not only what the whole Sum of all and every Aid granted or to be granted to his Majeſty, will or doth amount unto in every Townſhip, Pariſh, Diviſion, Hundred, and County of the whole Kingdom; but may alſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily diſcover, that whereas his Majeſty now loſeth one fourth, if not the third Part of his Aids given him by Anticipations, Loanes at Intereſt, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Prizes for Proviſions, Intereſt Money for Payments in Courſe, Fees to Collect, and Charges to Remit them after Collections, Fees upon Receipt and Payment of them, Contracts with Farmers and Undertakers, and twenty things more that I liſt not to mention. He ſhall now have not only all or the moſt part of thoſe Expences ſaved, and his Revenue ſetled and determined what it is, but alſo the ſame augmented ſome hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds by the Year, every Year ſo long as it ſhall be continued.</p>
            <p>This may ſatisfy for the way of Collecting his Majeſties Treaſure whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Hearths or Excize, and in general of all other Aids whatſoever, that are or may be given him by his Parliament, and laid upon the Nation in General.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:110745:9"/>As to the Payment of this Treaſure, thus Collected and Lodged in the Subjects own Hands (which will much content them,) I ſhall further offer to Conſideration theſe Propoſitions following, which I doubt not will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and pleaſe them much more, if due Care and Fidelity be had and uſed therein.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, That the Treaſurers both of the Navy, Army, and Houſhold or other Treaſurers of his Majeſties Revenues reſpectively, be required and enabled by Act of Parliament to receive and Pay the ſame, as the Sole Truſtees thereof, for the Uſe and Service of his Majeſty, and for no other Uſe or Service whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, That all Treaſures, Aydes and Collections ſo Veſted in the ſaid Treaſurers, by the ſeveral Acts of Parliament, ſhall not be diverted or paid by them or any of them, to any other Uſe or Service, than for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices proper and peculiar to their reſpective Truſts, whether in the Army, Navy, Houſhold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or by any other Order or Warrant, than the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Warrant of three or more of the Commiſſioners for the Treaſury, three or more of the Commiſſioners of the Navy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that if they or any of them, ſhall preſume to pay any part thereof, to any other Uſe than the Payment of his Majeſties due Debts, according to their ſeveral Truſts, by any other Order or Warrant, than the ordinary Warrant of that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, whereof they are Treaſurers, that they by the ſaid Act, he or they ſhall be liable to ſuch Puniſhment as his Majeſty with his Parliament ſhall think fit to lay upon him or them, for his or their Breach of Truſt in that behalf. And that the Auditors of their Accounts, reſpectively be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and impowred by the ſaid Act or Acts of Parliament, not to give him or them any Allowance of any of his Majeſties Treaſure ſo paid by any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trajudicial Warrant, or Order upon any Pretence whatſoever, upon all or any of their preſent or ſucceeding Accompts, upon pain of loſing their Places, and ſuffering what other Puniſhment his Majeſty and his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall think fit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, That the Commiſſioners of each County nominated in the ſaid Act or Acts, be impowred and required ſpeedily to ſend up to the ſaid Treaſurers, under the Hands and Seals of ſix or more of them, a Liſt or Certificate of what Sum or Sums of Money are Due and Payable to his Majeſty by the ſaid County, as their Part of the whole Sum granted for three or ſix Months, according to the ſeveral Acts for the ſame, and therein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare how the ſame is by them and their fellow-Commiſſioners, diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into ſo many Hundreds as are in that County, and into ſo many Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as are in each Hundred, and into ſo many Pariſhes as are in each Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, and into ſo many Townſhips as are in each Pariſh. And to ſignify in the ſaid Certificate the Names of the reſpective Collectors of every Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, together with the diſtinct Sums of Money charged upon them, and Collected by them, whether for the Hearth Money, Excize, or the Navy diſtinctly, whereby the ſaid Treaſurers may at one view, have and ſee not only the full Sum payable by every Hundred in the ſaid County, but alſo by every Diviſion in the ſaid Hundred, every Pariſh in the ſaid Diviſion, and every Townſhip in the ſaid Pariſh for three Months, and where and in whoſe Hands the ſame and every part thereof is Lodged for his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Service.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, That the like Certificate or Liſt be alſo ſent up to the ſaid
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110745:10"/>Treaſurors under Hands and Seals of two or more of the Commiſſioners of every City or Town Corporate, chargable in the ſaid Act or Acts, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of that Sum that is charged upon each County, as part or member thereof for three Months.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fifthly, That when the Treaſurer of the Navy, or any other Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer hath received the aforeſaid Liſts, Certificate, or Duplicates of every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Hundred, Diviſion, Rape, Wapentake, City, and Town in the whole Kingdom, charged with all or any part of the Sum mentioned in the ſaid Act or Acts, he or they the ſaid Treaſurers be further required, and by the ſaid Acts Impowred to give publick Notice at the common Office of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy or other Places, where their reſpective Truſts are to be executed, to all men that have or ſhall ſell any Proviſions, Commodities, Goods, or Wares to his Majeſty, or others Authorized by him for his Uſe in the Navy, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Place, where his Service requires them, and are thereby become Creditors to his Majeſty, for any Sum of Money whatſoever, that they and every of them ſhall forthwith bring to his, and their Offices reſpectively, all ſuch Bills, Orders, Warrant, or Debentures Signed and Atteſted in the due form of the Office of the Navy, Army, Houſhold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by three or more of thoſe that are or ſhall be Authorized to give Warrant for all Payments referring to their particular and reſpective Truſts, and there to put their Hands as for the Receipt of ſo much Money as ſhall juſtly appear to be due upon the ſame, after due Examination had thereof by the ſaid Treaſurers and their Deputies and Inſtruments, and after Defaulkation made of all Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſts formerly paid thereupon.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Sixthly, That the ſaid Treaſurers be in like manner Impowred and Required by the ſaid Acts to call for and take up all Bills of Impreſſes Signed and paid in the due form of their ſeveral Offices, to any Perſon or Perſons that have or ſhall contract for any Proviſions, referring to the Navy, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Houſhold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be afterwards ſupplyed and ſerved into his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Stores for the preſent and future Service.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Sevently, That the ſaid Treaſurers for the time being, reſpectively be required and by the ſaid Acts Impowred upon Receipt and Delivery of all and every ſuch Bills of Emptions or other ordinary Warrants, Debentures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to give to the reſpective Parties from whom they do or ſhall receive the ſame, one or more Aſſignations under his or their Hands and Seals, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one or more of the ſaid Counties, Hundreds, Diviſions, Pariſhes and Townſhips, moſt remore from <hi>London,</hi> of ſo much of his Majeſties Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure veſted in them by the ſaid Acts, as ſhall Pay and Diſcharge each Mans Bill or Debenture, Order or Warrant, therein Charging, and in his Majeſties Name requiring all to whom the ſaid Aſſignations ſhall come or concern, to pay the ſame to him or them, or their lawful Aſſigns upon ſight thereof, if then due, or ſo ſoon as the ſame ſhall appear to be, and grow due, by and from the ſaid Counties, Hundreds, Diviſions, Pariſhes and Townſhips by Vertue of the ſaid Act or Acts of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Which Aſſignation ſo Signed and Sealed as aforeſaid, ſhall be (and by the ſaid Acts ſhall be expreſſed to be) as good and ſufficient Security to the reſpective Parties, for their ſeveral Debts due from his Majeſty, as if they had ſtill kept their Bills and Debentures for the ſame, and upon Payment thereof by the County, Hundred, Diviſion, Pariſh, and Townſhip, and the Collectors thereof reſpectively, upon whom it is charged or drawn, the like
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110745:10"/>good and ſufficient Security, and Diſcharge for and to the ſaid County, Hundred, Diviſion, Pariſh, and Townſhip, and the reſpective Collectors, and all other men whatſoever concerned therein, as if they and every of them had paid the ſame according to former Cuſtom, to the high Collector, Receiver General, or Farmers of his Majeſties Revenues.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Eightly, That the ſaid Treaſurers be enabled by the ſaid Acts (if the Parties ſhall deſire it) to include in one and the ſame Aſſignation, as one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Sum, all ſuch Money as ſhall appear due, to or upon eight, ten, twelve or more Bills or Debentures, Orders or Warrants to 8. 19. 12. or more men that ſhall amicably Conſent and Agree among themſelves, to employ one or more men for them all, to receive the Sum aſſigned from the reſpective Counties, Hundreds, Diviſions, Pariſhes and Townſhips, provided that they and every of the ſaid Treaſurers do ſpecify in the body of his and their Aſſignations each mans diſtinct Name, Bill and Sum of Money due to him in particular, though he chargeth the County, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but with one Total.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Ninthly, That all Commiſſioners nominated in and by the ſaid Acts for all and every County, be required to be Aiding and Aſſiſting to all and every ſuch Perſon or Perſons, that ſhall preſent or produce to them or any of them, any Aſſignation upon that County, Hundred, Diviſion, Pariſh, or Townſhip within the ſame, by giving Warrants of Diſtreſs to all Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and other Officers in caſe of Refuſal or Delay of Payment thereof af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame ſhall appear due to his Majeſty or his Aſſigns by the reſpective Acts of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Tenthly, That the Comptroller of the Navy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (or ſuch other Perſon or Perſons as his Majeſty and the Parliament ſhall think fit to appoint) be Required and Impowred by vertue of the ſaid Acts, to take and keep an exact Counter-Check, or Book of Accompts, by way of Charge and Diſcharge, or Creditor and Debtor, of all Bills, Debentures, Orders and Warrants, that ſhall be taken up by the ſaid Treaſurers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, and of all Aſſignations thereupon given by them or any of them, to all or any of his Majeſties Subjects or Creditors, therein ſpecifying the particular Sums of Money due to the reſpective Perſons upon the ſaid Bills, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and payable by the ſaid Aſſignations, to them or their lawful Aſſigns, by and from the reſpective Counties, Hundreds, Diviſions, Pariſhes, and Townſhips, as the ſame ſhall grow due to his Majeſty, by Vertue of the ſaid Acts, for Beer and Ale, Chymnies, or any other thing or way whatſoever. And that no Bill, Debenture, Order, or Warrant be taken in by them or any of them the ſaid Treaſurers, nor any Aſſignation be thereupon given by the ſaid Treaſurers or any of them without the Preſence, Privity. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, and Atteſtation of the ſaid Comptroller, or ſuch other Perſon or Perſons, as his Majeſty and his Parliament, ſhall pleaſe to appoint in and by the ſaid Acts.</p>
            <p>Theſe things premiſed, I ſhall endeavour to vindicate this Propoſition from ſome of thoſe Objections that may be made againſt it, either as not Practicable at all, or if it be, yet with ſo much Diſadvantage and Dammage to his Majeſty, that it will not become the Honour of his Majeſty, nor the Wiſdom of the Parliament to ſettle it after this manner.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It may be ſaid that all his Majeſties Treaſure ought regularly to be brought into, and lodged in his Exchequer before it be Iſſued to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:110745:11"/>
               <hi>To which I Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I am not at all againſt the way of the Exchequer, when the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice may admit of Formalities without Prejudice to its ſelf (which ought in the firſt place to be regarded) but if the Aides and Revenues ſetled or to be ſetled upon his Majeſty, whether Land Taxes, Hearth Money, Excize, or any other of the nature of theſe, referring to the Nation in General, cannot be Collected nor Paid into his Majeſties Exchequer, without the loſs of much Time, and the expence of too much of the ſame Treaſure, and that by this or any other way that may be found out, his Majeſty ſhall not only expedite the Collection as to time, but alſo facilitate, if not totally annihilate the Charge and Loſs that attends its Tranſmiſſion into the Exchequer: I ſee no Reaſon, why we ſhould ſo far dote upon a Formality (eſpecially in time of War) as to expoſe his Majeſty to ſo great and inſufferable a Loſs, only to keep up that Obſervance in ſtrict Mode and Form.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor indeed is the Treaſure of Hearth Money, and Excize, paid at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent into his Majeſties Exchequer, as by the Objection it is ſuppoſed it ought to be, but they are both farmed to ſeveral Undertakers, and the Money con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted for, is paid by them into the Exchequer, and no more. And what his Majeſty gains by farming of them, is eaſy to be told. It is true, he ſaves the Charge of Collecting, and Remitting it into his Exchequer, by theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, but it is as true that the Remedy is by ſo much worſe than the Diſeaſe, by how much his Majeſties Loſs, in and by theſe Contracts and Farmes, is greater than the Charge of Collecting and Remitting the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure into his Exchequer. Whereas in the Way Propoſed, his Majeſty ſhall be at no Charge in Collecting, nor yet in Paying into or out of his Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, what ſhall be Collected for his Service, and beſides all this, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable Loſs that now he undergoes by Farming, ſhall alſo be ſaved.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Suppoſe it Convenient to Lodge all his Majeſties Treaſure in his Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, when it may be done without loſs of Time, or Expence of Treaſure, as the common Receptacle of his Majeſties whole Revenue, doth it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow, that it may not be paid elſwhere, when both theſe Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that now attend it, may thereby be prevented; if it were paid into the Exchequer, muſt it not be paid from thence to ſatisfy his Majeſties Debts, to the ſame Men that this Propoſition deſigns it for, and when it is Paid do not all Inſtruments employed in the Exchequer, diſcharge themſelves of it in their Accompts, by thoſe Bills and Debentures, Orders, and Warrants, that give them Power ſo to pay it.</p>
            <p>The Deſign of the Exchequer, is principally for the Accompts of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Revenues, and not ſo much for the Receipt of the Treaſure it ſelf; Now if the Accompts of his Majeſties Treaſure, may be made in his Exchequer, as regularly as if it had been brought thither in <hi>Specie,</hi> though it never came there (as all Farmes, and Contracts for theſe Aides never did) then there can be nothing of Prejudice to his Majeſties Service in this Propoſition, though by it the Treaſure be deſigned to be paid where it is Collected, to wit, in <hi>Yorke, Plymouth, Briſtol, Yarmouth,</hi> and all other Places of the Nation: The Truth is, none but Men Intereſted in the Receit of theſe Aides, will make this Objection, nor they neither, but as it refers to their private Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, by being paid there, and no where elſe, and by themſelves, and no other Men.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:110745:11"/>4. Nor is the way propounded, altogether a Stranger to the Practiſe of late Times. There are many yet living, that do know, and can well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that in the Years 1635. 36. 37. 38 and 39. all the Treaſure that was then required and advanced by his then Majeſty, from his Subjects, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Name and Notion of Ship-Money, was by ſpecial Order from his Majeſty and Council, Veſted in the Hands, of the then Treaſurer of the Navy, who was by ſpecial Order, Enabled to Receive and Pay the ſame, without ever being brought into the Exchequer, and Limited to Pay all and every Part thereof; to and for the Uſe and Debts of the Navy (as Ship-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney) and not otherwiſe, as Part of the ordinary Charge of the Navy, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ships thereof employed at Sea, in all or any of theſe Years. And upon this Account it was that his Majeſty would not ſuffer it to be brought into his Exchequer, that it might not be diverted to any other Service, than the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Ship-Money, ſo called, that he might the better ſatisfy his Subjects, that what he did in Levying that Treaſure from them, was in Order to their own Preſervation, and not at all for any private Advantage to himſelf.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Yea give me Leave to tell you, that at preſent his Majeſties Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue of the Cuſtoms, and Impoſts, though it lies ſo near <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> that it may without much loſs of Time or Expence of Monies, be paid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Majeſties Exchequer, yet (for the greateſt Part thereof) it is not ſo Paid, nor doth it follow, that what part thereof is not Paid in there, muſt of Neceſſity be Iſſued thence, and from no other Place whatſoever, for the Uſe of his Majeſties Service; But the common Way is for all Gold-Smiths, and others that do lend his Majeſty any Money at Intereſt, to carry on his Services, before his own Revenue be Collected, to ſtrike Tallies upon the Commiſſioners or Farmers of the Cuſtoms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for their reſpective Loanes, with Intereſt Included in thoſe Tallies, and they do receive their Debts, not from the Exchequer, but from the Treaſurer of the Cuſtoms, as the ſame ſhall grow due upon their Tallies. Now if this Courſe hath been, is, and may be Practiſed for the future, without Prejudice to his Majeſties Service, though the Revenues of the Cuſtoms be not Paid into his Majeſties Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, I would humbly demand why the ſame Latitude may not be given and taken for the Payment of his Majeſties Revenues of Hearth-Mony, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize or Land Taxes in any other place of the Nation, by Aſſignation, from the reſpective Treaſurers, in whoſe Hands the ſame is Veſted by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, which is to them as good a Warrant (if not a greater) than any Talley ſtricken in his Majeſties Exchequer, can be to the Commiſſioners of the Cuſtoms, eſpecially conſidering that by this Means his Majeſty ſhall ſave the Intereſt Money allowed the Goldſmiths or others, upon their reſpective Tallies, and alſo the charge of Collecting and Paying it into his Exchequer, and the Fees allowed upon its Receipt there, and Payment thence. And that the Subject ſhall reap the Benefit of the ſpeedy Payment, without much Charge or Trouble.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If it be ſaid the Way propounded, muſt needs be very Chargable, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous and Troubleſom to the Subject before he can poſſibly compaſs his Aſſignation, or the Money Payable thereby, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That though I propound the Treaſure to be Paid in the Country, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110745:12"/>not out of the Exchequer, nor yet by the reſpective Treaſurers that are now truſted to Receive and Pay the ſame, but by private Men that have the Money in their Hands, and to ſuch as bring to them Aſſignations for it from the Treaſurers, yet theſe Men that Receive it, are ſuch Men as have Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted Debts to themſelves by Proviſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sold to his Majeſties Uſe, or for Service done him, and ſuch as (before they had their Aſſignations for it) had Bills, Debentures, Orders, and Warrants for their reſpective Debts, in the ordinary Way of the Offices of the Navy, Army, Houſhold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſuch as did by their Receipts to them acknowledg full Satisfaction of them, upon the Delivery of their premiſed Aſſignations, and being ſuch and ſo quallified, what is the Difference between their Receiving their Money or Debts at <hi>York</hi> (if they be content there to take it) or at <hi>London,</hi> at a Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Shop, upon a Ticket or Aſſignation from the ſame Man or Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, eſpecially conſidering that the firſt is ſetled (as I propound it to be) by Act of Parliament, and the laſt is a Deſign of the Treaſurers and their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments (never practiſed till a few Years Paſt.) Is it not better and more eaſie for the Subject to take and Receive his Debt, where he knows it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready Lodged by Act of Parliament (though far diſtant from <hi>London</hi>) than to dance Attendance upon the Treaſurer and his Inſtruments many Months before he can procure an Aſſignation to the Goldſmith, and when he hath it, to be as far from his Debt as he was before, unleſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But Secondly. The Novelty of this Propoſition, doth not render it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable for the Subject, nor doth it follow, that becauſe it was never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented, nor ſo much as Propounded before, that it may not be propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed now, and practiſed hereafter, if upon due and ſerious Conſideration had thereupon, it ſhall be found both Honourable and Highly Beneficial to his Majeſty, the Parliament, and the Subject, to make Uſe of it.</p>
            <p>As to his Majeſty, I dare boldly (yet humbly) Affirm that in the two ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Aides of Hearth-Money, and Excize, he ſhall ſave (what is now loſt) ſome hundred thouſand of Pounds by the Year, and could without much Difficulty make it appear by an Induction of Particulars, were it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and not too much reflecting upon Intereſted Men.</p>
            <p>As to the Parliament, the Way propoſed will enable them to ſee what they have given to his Majeſty by this or that Aid, and to determine upon View thereof, whether it be needful for them to grant him more, yea or not, which (as it is now carryed) they are not able to do, for though they know they have given him the Excize upon Ale, the Hearth Money, and other Aids and Revenues, yet they neither do nor can know, what one, both, all, or any one of theſe Aids do mount unto in the Total by the Year, and for want thereof are neceſſitated to Act upon an Implicite Faith, in giving more when it may be what they have already given, is enough.</p>
            <p>As to the Subject, the way propoſed is no more (nor indeed ſo much) as he voluntarily puts himſelf upon, in his Trading and Dealing with all Chapmen, in all parts of the Kingdom, to whom after he hath Sold and Truſted his Goods, he doth conſtantly once or twice every Year make his Application in his own Perſon, or by his Inſtruments, to Collect and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Debts from them, whereſoever they Dwell, and oft times with ill Succeſs, when the Debter by ill Husbandry or other Croſs, or Caſualty, is become Poor and Inſolvent (which yet in the way Propoſed can never be ſuppoſed in his Majeſty or the Parliament) yea we know that all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110745:12"/>that Trade for <hi>Ireland, Spain, France,</hi> the <hi>Streights, Barbadoes, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia,</hi> New <hi>England,</hi> yea the <hi>Eaſt Indies</hi> do run great Hazards, and are at greater Trouble and Charge in procuring their Debts, than poſſibly are or can be Imagined to be, attending thoſe that do or ſhall truſt his Majeſty in the Navy, Army, or Houſhold, if this way of Aſſignations for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Debts were vigorouſly put into Practiſe, and they thereby aſſured, that upon Demand of their Money, due upon their reſpective Aſſignations, they ſhould be duly and punctually paid without Snips, Fees, Gratuities, Delayes, or other Abatements, or Charges whatſoever, other than their neceſſary Expences, to Collect and Receive them.</p>
            <p>What better Security can they have or deſire to have than the King, Lords and Commons? what quicker Payment, than from the Collectors of every Townſhip, Pariſh, Diviſion, Hundred or County? what greater Power than upon Denial or Delay to diſtrein the Parties Goods, and ſell them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Face, and that by Authority of the Parliament, and that not ſo much by himſelf, as the Conſtable or other Officer, upon the place re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and impowred by Act of Parliament ſo to do. Add to this that all or moſt Tradeſmen in <hi>London,</hi> that ſhall or may ſerve his Majeſty with Proviſions for the Navy, Army, Houſhold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> came firſt out of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Counties of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> to be Apprentices there, and ſtill have their reſpective Friends, Relations, and Acquaintance remaining there, by whoſe Inſluence their Charge and Trouble may be much Facilitated. And I do not underſtand why thoſe that either do or ſhall deal with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty or his Commiſſioners for his Uſe, ſhould not as equally be content to take their Debts or Aſſignations from private Men, where thoſe Men have it for them, as from other private Men of the ſame place, to whom they have Sold, and voluntarily Truſted their Goods, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> Eſpecially conſidering that his Majeſty not only hath it there, where it is aſſigned them, but alſo that his Majeſty and his Parliament, have of purpoſe Lodged it there, that it might not be diverted from them to any Uſe or Purpoſe whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if once the Subject finds the Benefit, Security, and Sweetneſs of this way of Payment, and be thereby encouraged to deal farther with his Majeſties Commiſſioners, or other Officers, as knowing by Experience their Aſſignations certain and punctual (as to Payment) then the ſaid Commiſſioners and Officers may and ſhall make their Contracts at eaſier Rates, by at leaſt 8 <hi>l. per Cent.</hi> in the Price, than now they either do or can do, (beſides the unſerviceableneſs of the Proviſion it ſelf) for every Man is at preſent loath to deal with his Majeſties Officers, for any conſiderable quantity of Goods, unleſs they be prickt forward thereto by the profit of 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> in the Price, more than they would willingly ſell the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity for to a private Man, if that Man be a good ſolvent and punctual Man as to his Payment, whereas if his Majeſties Payment were certain, they would then ſeek the Service of his Majeſtie. Officers and Commiſſioners ſhould never want any Proviſion they deſire to have, better for and at far eaſier Rates than now they can procure them, by reaſon of the uncertain Way of Payment, and theſe not be named Snips, Abatements, and Allowan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (beſides the length of time) that are and muſt be made before they can compaſs their Money.</p>
            <p>I ſhall further add that if it were true that the Subject ſhould (by the way Propoſed) be at as great a Charge and Trouble as his Majeſty is now at in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110745:13"/>remitting his Treaſure into his Exchequer (which yet cannot rationally be imagined) yet is it not better that 20000 Men or more ſhould divide and bear the Charge and Loſs among themſelves, than that the whole Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then ſhould lye upon one Mans Shoulder, or his Majeſties ſingle Perſon, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially conſidering, (as we ſay) that the <hi>Medium</hi> will bear it (as to them) I mean that the Profit in the Price of their Proviſions will bear it, and much more, whereas his Majeſty loſeth what he loſeth, be it more or leſs, out of the quick Stock. I mean his ſetled Revenue.</p>
            <p>Let me further ſay, that it is ſafer and more rational (yea it is practical in all common Nuſances,) that ſome few Men in the Nation, ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bear the Loſs and Charge of that Nuſance, than that the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould ſuffer under it, as they do in the Caſe in Hand. For to ſpeak plainly, it is not ſo much his Majeſty that loſeth what is loſt (though that be a Truth in ſome Sence) as the People of the Nation that pay it, who indeed pay and loſe it twice over. Firſt out of their Purſes and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, by paying it according to the Act, and Secondly in its not being em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed upon the Service for which the Act requires it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In ſhort,</hi> I am partly confident, and for the greateſt part thereof could make it appear (were it not to avoid Offence) that his Majeſty loſeth the fourth, if not the third Part of all his Treaſure given him by ſeveral Acts of Parliament, before it can arrive to a nett Payment in the due Form of all Offices, and we know that the one fourth Part of two Millions, is in the whole 500000 <hi>l.</hi> Now whether it be ſafe for his Majeſty or his Parliament to ſuffer ſo great a Dammage to attend the Service upon which the Welfare of the whole Nation depends, if they can prevent it, I humbly ſubmit to their more ſerious Conſideration, and ſhall only ſay that by means of this Propoſition, the Treaſurer of the Navy, and all other Treaſurers may be conſtantly furniſhed with Treaſure ſufficient, and more than enough to pay off all growing Debts upon his Majeſty, whether by Intereſt or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and after a more eſpecial manner, that devouring Monſter of Seamens Wages before mentioned, ſo ſoon as the reſpective Fleets or Ships ſhall be ſafe at their Moarings, the want whereof in the late War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> was a moſt intollerable Diſſervice to his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>To conclude, I ſhall humbly leave it to the Wiſdom of his Majeſty, and his Parliament, to conſider that the way propoſed cuts off all Capability in the reſpective Treaſurers of Diverting all or any part of his Majeſties Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, already or hereafter to be granted to him, to or for any other Uſe or Uſes than the Payment of his Majeſties Debts, duly made in their reſpective Offices, to which it is aſſigned, which (if I miſtake not) no other way as yet Propoſed or Practiſed can prevent or diſappoint. And if there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe of Weight or Worth in this Propoſition, that might invite its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment; Yet this it ſelf duly conſidered, is enough to out-Ballance all Objections, that are or can be made againſt it. The Truth is, though I could frame as many Objections againſt the Way propoſed, as moſt of thoſe that ſhall ſet themſelves to oppoſe it, yet I cannot ſee any of them, of that weight and conſideration that ſome may think them to be, and truly if I did, I ſhould readily relinquiſh all Thoughts upon it, as Idle and Vain, having no De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign by it, either againſt any mans Perſon or Welfare, or for any private Profit or Preferment to my ſelf, but intirely to ſerve his Majeſty and my Country, as becometh a dutiful Subject in theſe Diſtracted Times which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110745:13"/>call aloud for every mans Help to preſerve his Majeſty from Debt and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, and his Subjects from all unneceſſary Burthens. If his Majeſty and Parliament ſhall not think fit to make uſe of it, I can as well content my ſelf, as if they did, I ſhall acquieſce in their deep Wiſdom, though yet I think I ſhall never live to ſee his Majeſty freed from thoſe Debts that are now upon him, and do and will grow more and greater, notwithſtanding, all the forementioned Ways and Means now uſed to free him from them; Intereſt Money, and other Improvidences not fit to be named, though yet notoriouſly known, being as equally deſtructive to his Majeſties Revenues, as they are to a private Mans Eſtate, if not truly and carefully prevented.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>ALthough I have in the former Diſcourſe propounded the Payment of his Majeſties Aids, whether ordinary or extraordinary, whether by Land-Taxes, Excize, Hearth-Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be made to the Subject by Aſſignations from the reſpective Treaſurers, upon the Collectors of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Townſhips, yet if it ſhall be thought too much Charge or Trouble to the Subject to receive their Debts by theſe Aſſignations, from the Hands of ſo many Collectors, thus diſtributed and diſtinguiſhed, I ſhall humbly offer, that the Money or Treaſure collected in each Townſhip, may be paid and depoſited into the Hands of one or more Men, to be intruſted to receive the whole Collection of each Pariſh, and if it be ſtill thought too great Trouble to the Subject to receive it from him or them, then that the Treaſure Collected in that Pariſh (as alſo in all Pariſhes in that Diviſion) be paid over and depoſited into the Hands of one two or more of that Diviſion, as the total Sum aſſeſſed upon or ariſing from that Diviſion. And if yet it ſhall not be thought fit to burthen the Subject with ſo much Trouble and Charge as may attend the Receipt thereof from the reſpective Truſtees of each Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that then the whole Sum Collected in that Diviſion (as alſo in all the Diviſions of that Hundred) be paid and depoſited into the Hands of two or more able and reſponſible Men of that Hundred. And further if the Treaſure Collected in that Hundred, be not thought fit to be paid by thoſe Intruſted therewith, to thoſe that ſhall bring or preſent Aſſignations from the reſpective Treaſurers, for all or any part thereof, that then the Money Collected in that Hundred (and in all Hundreds of that County) be it more or leſs, be paid over to one two or more Commiſſioners to be nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated and appointed by the ſeveral Acts of Parliament, as receivers of the ſame for the whole County, to be by them paid to the Subject, according to ſuch Aſſignations as he or they ſhall from time to time receive from the reſpective Treaſurers for the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:110745:14"/>This I am ſure, (if none of the reſt) will both eaſe the Charge, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitate the Trouble of the Subject, and yet preſerve his Majeſties Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue intire, and abundantly Satisfy the Parliament, whether what they have given to his Majeſty be ſufficient for that end, for which it was given, or not.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid that this Remedy is full as bad (if not worſe) than the Diſeaſe, in regard his Majeſty and the Parliament muſt by this Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be at the Charge of ſo many Commiſſioners for the Receipt and Payment of his Treaſure, as there be Counties in the Nation, or Hundreds in each County of the Nation; and that this Charge and Expence will amount to as much if not more than if the whole Aid were remitted into his Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and paid thence according to the preſent ſetled and regular Way of the Nation.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, No ſuch Matter, for indeed the whole Charge cannot rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſuppoſed to be the Moyety of his Majeſties Charge, into and out of the Exchequer, as I could eaſily demonſtrate to all unbyaſſed Men. But to wave that diſpute, I ſhall further ſay that though by this Propoſition I do deſign the eaſe of the Subject as to Charge and Trouble in Collecting his Aſſignations, yet I conceive it Juſt and Reaſonable that the whole Charge of Collecting and Paying it from the reſpective Pariſhes to the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners for each Diviſion, and from them to Commiſſioners of each Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and from them to the Commiſſioners of each County, and from them to the Creditors that ſhall preſent their Aſſignations, may and ought in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part thereof, to be born by the Subject that receives the Treaſure, and no part thereof paid or born by his Majeſty, in regard what is done by his Majeſty or his Parliament in this Particular, is ſo done for the Subjects eaſe and benefit, and not his Majeſties, and in regard all Creditors have either by Intereſt-Money or the Profit of their Goods Sold, or both Inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the ſame Aſſignation, ſufficient Gains to bear that and a greater Loſs, and are alſo inabled to Receive their Money Aſſigned them without all or any of that Charge, that now attends him or them, by Fees, Gratuities, or otherwiſe, before he or they can procure it paid in other Offices or Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and alſo that he or they do and ſhall come into it, in a far ſhorter time, than otherwiſe he or they could obtain it, either by ſtaying for it till there comes Money in the reſpective Offices to pay them, or by carrying his or their Bills, Debentures, Orders, or Warrants, and entering them as ſo much Money lent unto his Majeſty, to be paid with Intereſt in courſe. All which conſidered and laid together, is I am ſure a far greater Profit and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the Subject, than the premiſed Charge and Loſs can poſſibly be, and will eaſily ſatisfy them that the Charge of Lodging their Debts after this manner for them, whether in Counties or Hundreds, ought to be born by themſelves, and no part thereof by his Majeſty. And I am confident that if the Parliament ſhould think fit to declare in their reſpective Acts, what, and how much the Charge ſhall be to the Subject in the Receipt of his Aſſignations, either to the Juſtices Clarkes, the Collectors of each Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion or Hundred, or to the Commiſſioners of each County and their Clarks, as they have formerly done in Acts of Parliament, for Land Taxes to men of the ſame or the like Truſts, that the Subject would be ſo far from Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content or Diſſatisfaction therein, that it would incourage him to deal with his Majeſties Commiſſioners in the future for all Goods, Ships or other things
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110745:14"/>whatſoever with more Confidence and Chearfulneſs, and at eaſier Rates, by far than formerly they did. For ſuppoſe an Aſſignation be given for one thouſand Pounds, and that the Charge attending its Receipt, be by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, declared to be three pence upon the Pound, to be diſtributed to ſeveral Inſtruments, the whole Charge of the Receipt of his 1000 <hi>l.</hi> is but 12 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> 00. And what Creditor to his Majeſties Service would grutch to give 12 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> (which is but 25 <hi>s</hi> out of a hundred Pounds) as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Fees ſpent out of the whole thouſand Pounds Debt from his Majeſty, to ſave his own Pains and Labour, that hath not only the profit of the Price of his Goods ſold, but alſo Intereſt-Money allowed him for the whole 1000 <hi>l.</hi> incluſively, in his Aſſignation till his Money be paid. But admit the worſt, to wit, that the Charge of the Receipt of his 1000 <hi>l</hi> were much more (as ſomething it muſt needs be by Travel, Exchange, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) yet (as was ſaid before) is not this Burthen lighter upon the Shoulders of 20000 Men or more in the whole Nation, than to be laid upon, and born by his Majeſties ſingle Perſon, eſpecially conſidering (as was ſaid) that the profit will bear much more loſs, and yet leave them ſufficient Gainers by his Majeſties Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and that at preſent, they are at far greater loſs of Time and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence out of their principal Debt, before they can compaſs it to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But ſuppoſe his Majeſty and his Parliament ſhould approve of this Propoſition, in any of the Notions held forth in this Poſtſcript: how ſhould thoſe Creditors to whom his Majeſty is indebted, either by voluntary Loans, Anticipations, Advance-Money upon Farms or Contracts, Orders in Courſe or otherwiſe, be paid their reſpective Debts, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> Where Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts are made, and Farms lett, it is both Juſt and Honourable that the Farmers ſhould enjoy the Benefit of their Contracts, upon which they did lend or advance their Money during the whole term of their Contract unexpired. The ſame alſo might be ſaid in the Caſe of Anticipations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any part of his Majeſties Revenue, where Tallies are ſtruck upon them till the Tallies be fully paid; but for voluntary Loans, Orders in Courſe, and other occaſional Debts, the ſooner they were paid off by Aſſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon his Majeſties Aids thus ſetled and depoſited in each County or Hundred the better, in order to take off that eating Charge of Intereſt-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, that devours too great a Part thereof.</p>
            <p>What if after all this Care taken, it ſhall appear that the preſent Aids ſetled upon his Majeſty, are not enough or ſufficient to bear about his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Expences in ordinary, and much leſs to pay off his Debts, and how ſhall his Majeſty carry on his Service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by propounding to his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his neceſſity of further Aids from his People, and having it granted to him, when all the care taken that can be to improve the preſent Aides given him to the higheſt of Frugality, and found too little?</p>
            <p>Were it not better for his Majeſty to proceed in the preſent way of Loans, Anticipations, Farms, Payments in Courſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than to depend upon the Love or Bounty of his Parliament and People, eſpecially conſidering how ready and willing the City of <hi>London,</hi> the Goldſmiths now called Bankers, and other his Majeſties Subjects, are to ſupply his Neceſſities upon all emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Occaſions, out of their Zeal and Affection to and for his Majeſties Service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Why ſhould his Majeſty be directed to a ſtanding Pool to quench his Thirſt, that hath a River to drink in? What Zeal or Affection, either do thoſe that lend or advance Treaſure, ſhew to his Majeſty more
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110745:15"/>than I can have from a Common Uſurer in my Neceſſity, if I can but give him ſuch Security as he likes for the Payment of his Principal with Intereſt, Do I look upon him as a man that loves me, who notwithſtanding all his fair Pretences to me, will not lend me 5000 <hi>l</hi> to relieve me, unleſs I will mortgage to him my Eſtate for the Security of his 500 <hi>l</hi> with Intereſt? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly as this is no Love to a private Man in his Neceſſity from an Uſurer, ſo it is much leſs to a Prince in his. And as this is no ſafe way for a private Man to take that hath a Father, Brother or Friend that is willing, able, and ready to furniſh his Wants without Intereſt or Mortgaging his Eſtate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo is a moſt deſtructive way to his Majeſty, who hath his Parliament, and his People, not only able and willing, but alſo bound in Duty as his Loyal and Loving Subjects, to give him ſufficient Aid and Relief, if they find (as by the way propoſed they eaſily may) that what they have already ſetled upon him is not enough. But how ſhall the Parliament prevent the Loan of Money at Intereſt, Anticipations by Goldſmiths, or any other men, if after all that is or may hereafter be ſetled upon him, his Majeſty ſhall yet deſire to borrow their Money.</p>
            <p>It would ſavour of too much boldneſs for any private man (and much more for my ſelf) to hint any thing in this Particular to the Wiſdom of the Parliament: They know better than any Man can direct them what to do in this Point, though yet I muſt needs ſay, that even in my own time, I have known it looked upon as a Criminal Act for any Man what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever to compound his Majeſties Debts, to ſtrike Tallies upon his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue with Intereſt included to pay them, or to advance Money upon Intereſt, to ſupply his Majeſties Occaſions upon any Account whatſoever, and do much fear that till ſome ſuch Courſe be taken with thoſe that grow upon his Majeſties Neceſſity by Anticipations, Loans, Farms, Advance Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or any other way whatſoever, with Intereſt allowed them for their Money; his Majeſty ſhall (as I have formerly ſaid) never be out of Debt, let the Parliament give him what they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>How ſhall his Majeſty have a clear and regular Accompt in his Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, of the full proceed of his Hearth-Money, Excize, and other his ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or to be ſetled Revenues in the way propoſed?</p>
            <p>But the Certificates, Liſts, and Duplicates, of all Treaſure Collected and Paid to the Commiſſioners of each Hundred or County, and by the Aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations made by the reſpective Treaſurers to the ſaid Commiſſioners, and by the Compter-Check of thoſe Aſſignations, all which will either by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or compared together, Ballance the Accompts of all Treaſurers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, and give the Auditor of thoſe Accompts ſufficient Grounds for his Allowance of the ſame, if paid according to the Direction of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Acts of Parliament in the uſual Form, and by the common Voucher of their Offices reſpectively, and not otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Who ſhall give the Treaſurers their reſpective Charges? The ſeveral Acts of Parliament where the Treaſure is aſcertained by a Land Tax, and in default thereof, as in the Caſe of Excize and Hearth-Money, the Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates of each Townſhip in every Pariſh, the Certificates of each Pariſh in all Diviſions, the Certificates of all Diviſions in every Hundred, the Certificates of all Hundreds in every County, and the Certificates of all Counties in the whole Kingdom: This I am ſure will give them, and each of them a full Charge.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:110745:15"/>But are not the Treaſurers notwithſtanding this, left in a Capacity of diverting his Majeſties Treaſure to wrong Perſons, and for wrong and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Services?</p>
            <p>Not at all, if the Acts of Parliament be their Rule and Guide for their Aſſignations, and the Contra-rotulator or Clerk of theſe Aſſignations be faithful to his Truſt.</p>
            <p>How ſhall the Townſhips of every Pariſh, the Pariſhes of every Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Diviſions of every Hundred, the Hundreds of every County, the Counties of the whole Kingdom, and every individual Perſon concerned in the Collection or Payment of all or any of his Majeſties Aides, or any part thereof, whether Land-Taxes, Hearth Money, or Excize, be acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of their reſpective payments.</p>
            <p>You might have ſpared your Enquiry if you had obſerved what was ſaid in the ſeventh Article of this Propoſition, yet to ſatisfy your Curioſity, I ſhall further ſay, that they either are or may be acquitted by the Receipts of the reſpective Collectors of every Townſhip, Pariſh, Diviſion, Hundred or County in the whole Nation, to be nominated or appointed either by the Acts of Parliament, or by Warrant from the Deputy-Lieutenant, Juſtices of the Peace, or others authorized by the ſaid Acts to appoint Aſſeſſors, and Collectors for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Will not the Way propoſed be a great Burthen to the reſpective Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers in making their Aſſignations, and the Comptroler in keeping Check upon them more than their proper Duty is at preſent, and will not this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get his Majeſty into a farther Charge than at preſent he is at for their ſo doing?</p>
            <p>As to the Treaſurers, their Labour will not be near ſo much as what they now do or ought to do in their Receipt and Payment of all Monies proper to their Places and Truſts, a great part whereof they are by this means totally caſed in, and freed from. And for the Aſſignations themſelves they have nothing to do therein, but to ſit up a Blank-printed Aſſignation of one and the ſame Form and Subſtance, varying only in the Date, the Sum Aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Place, County, Hundred, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Names of the Commiſſioners that are to pay it, and of the Parties that are to receive it; As to the Compt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercheck, it is at preſent, his proper Duty to check the Treaſurers Accompts of all Payments whatſoever, and in this Way he will be eaſed of much of that Labour, that now lies upon him, if he perform his Duty as he ought, ſo that his Majeſty may rather abate much of what is already allowed, than give more in a way of Augmentation.</p>
            <p>How ſhall the Treaſurers of the Navy, Army, Houſhold, or other men Intruſted for Payment of his Majeſties Treaſure by Aſſignations, be direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed where and upon whom to place and make their Aſſignments, without interfering each with other?</p>
            <p>By the Acts of Parliament, Aſſigning ſuch and ſo many Counties to each Treaſurer, as ſhall drown the Sum eſtimated to be the full Expence of each Office for one Year.</p>
            <p>If his Majeſties Revenues ſhould be paid by Aſſignations after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, from the reſpective Treaſurers, how or where ſhall his Majeſty be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with Treaſure ſufficient for his privy Purſe, Intelligence with For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Princes, and other extraordinary Expences Suitable to the Dignity of his Perſon?</p>
            <p>By and from the Cuſtomes, Excize, and Impoſts laid, and to be laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110745:16"/>all Native and Forraign Commodities Exported and Imported, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue whereof is not at all within the Ken, Compaſs or Proſpect of this Propoſition, but left wholy as it now is to be improved and imployed by his Majeſty, for thoſe and other Services, without Reference to the Way Propoſed for the Collection and Payment of his other Aides and Land-Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, that concern the Nation in General.</p>
            <p>In what particulars doth the Way Propoſed, tend to the Advantage of his Majeſty, or his Succeſſors.</p>
            <p>I love not Repetitions, yea have had them here and there ſcatteringly delivered through the whole Diſcourſe paſt, yet in the regard this is the Hing upon which the Deſign of this Propoſition doth turn, and the only Ground of my preſent undertaking; I ſhall (contrary to my Deſire, and the Practice of thoſe that know what they ſay or write) gratifie you with a particular enumeration of ſome few of thoſe many Advantages of no ſmall Conſideration that may accrue to his Majeſty by this Propoſition.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, In his Honour, it being much below the Dignity of a Prince, that hath a Rich, Loyal, and Loving People to his Subjects, willing and ready upon all emergencies to ſupply his Wants, to ſeek the Aid and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of private Perſons, that never Act without Deſigns of Profit and Gain to themſelves, in all their pretended Services for him, and without which they will not ſupply him.</p>
            <p>For his Majeſty to have Advice and to Proſecute this Way when he was under the Inhumane Uſage of the late Uſurpation was no wonder; Force hath no Choice; But for his Majeſty to be adviſed to the ſame Courſes now, when he is Crowned King of <hi>England,</hi> by thoſe that I dare ſay are his Faithful and Loyal Servants and Subjects, and to proſecute that Advice, when the Perſons and Purſes of the whole Nation are at his Devotion and Service, is much to his Diſhonour. The Long Parliament in the late un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy War, that firſt brought up the Payment of Orders in Courſe in this Nation, were not able to carry on the War without ſuch a way, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Peoples Diſaffection to them, and that the greateſt part of the Nation was then under the Power of the Kings Army; but this is no Rule, or Coppy for his Majeſties Friends or Servants to walk in, or write by, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they could make it appear that his Majeſty is at preſent in the ſame Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemma. When the War ceaſed, Payments in Courſe, ceaſed of Courſe. And why they ſhould be continued to his Majeſties great Dammage, and Diſhonor in this happy time of Peace, I cannot underſtand,</p>
            <p>If he hath not enough, in Gods Name let him have more, yea much more than enough, rather than one Penny too little; there is no Loyal Subject that will not ſay AMEN to this Prayer, only let not the Uſurer, Farmer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Eat out and Devour his Revenues, under the notion of high Services, and I know not what other Pretences.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In his Revenue of Excize, Hearth-Money, and all Land-Taxes, which by this Means may be improved to the utmoſt Pitch of what they are, be it more or leſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the Charge of Collecting the ſaid Revenues, which at preſent coſts his Majeſty, as allowed by the Acts of Parliament, for two Millions of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure 33333 <hi>l.</hi> 06 <hi>s.</hi> 08 <hi>d.</hi> all and every Part thereof being by the way Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be paid by the Subject that hath the Benefit of his Aſſignations.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the Fees allowed to all Officers and their Clerks in the Exchequer for the Receipt of his Majeſties Revenue.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:110745:16"/>By the like Fees Paid and Allowed to the ſame Officers, and their Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the payment of his Majeſties Treaſure, either to private Perſons; or to the reſpective Treaſurers of the Navy, Army, Houſhold, in their reſpective Offices to be paid by them to private Men for his Majeſties Uſe and Services.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In all Fees and Allowances made and given by the Auditors to all or any of theſe Treaſurers upon their Accompts as Money disburſed, as paid by them for Portage, Water-Carriage, Baggs, Wax, or any other Charge whatſoever in the Receipt of his Majeſties Treaſure, Aſſigned to them in their ſeveral Offices and Truſts.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In having by this means a Bank of Treaſure in all thoſe Countries that lie near <hi>London,</hi> ready upon all Commands to ſupply preſent Occaſions; All Aſſignations being by this Propoſition in the firſt place to be charged and given to, and upon all Counties remote from <hi>London,</hi> whether in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Hereby his Majeſty ſhall have Treaſure ready to pay off all Fleets or Ships ſo ſoon as they are ſafely gotten to their Moarings, to prevent that devouring Charge or Monſter of paying Victuals and Wages for twelve or thirteen Months before mentioned.</p>
            <p n="9">9. It enabling his Majeſties Commiſſioner in all Offices whatſoever to Contract and Purchaſe for his Majeſties Uſe and Service, all and all ſorts of Proviſions, far better in their kind, and by at leaſt eight or ten <hi>per Cent.</hi> cheaper in their Price, than they can poſſibly do in the way of Payment now Practiſed.</p>
            <p n="10">10. By cutting off all Intereſt-Money now paid to the Goldſmiths or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men for Moneys taken up by way of Anticipation, before his Majeſties Revenue can poſſibly be Collected and paid into his Majeſties Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer.</p>
            <p n="11">11. By the like ſaving of all Intereſt now paid and allowed upon all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Payable in Courſe either for Goods ſold, or Moneys lent upon that way of Payment.</p>
            <p n="12">12. By preventing the preſent Dammage ſuſtained by Farms and Contracts, upon all or any of his Majeſties Aides, wherein the profit to the Contractor is at leaſt one fourth, if not one third Part of what he undertakes for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Oppreſſion of the Subject.</p>
            <p n="13">13. By preventing all capability of Diverſion of his Majeſties Treaſure in all or any part thereof from the Services to which it was deſigned by the Parliament, when it was firſt granted to his Majeſty, eſpecially in the caſe of War, or any other extraordinary Service, where the Tax laid is a Land Tax, and refers to the Nation in General, and not to particular Perſons, ſo and ſo qualified as the Excize and Hearth-Mony do.</p>
            <p n="14">14. By capacitating the Victualler of his Majeſties Navy, to make his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of Victuals in all Sea-Ports and Harbours where any of his Majeſties Fleets or Ships ſhall lye, or may touch or come, ſuch as <hi>Dover, Harwich, New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>castle, Plymouth, Dartmouth, &amp;c.</hi> by taking up his Bills of Impreſt, and giving him Aſſignations upon thoſe Towns, Cities, or Counties, moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiguous to thoſe Parts, or Harbours whereby his Majeſties Ships ſhall or may be diſpatched to Sea, and not lie in Harbour full manned, ſometimes two Months together before he can get Victuals to ſend them forth to Sea.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:110745:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>15. In full and ſeaſonable Supplies of the Magazeens of all his Majeſties In-Stores and Out-Stores, in all and every of his Majeſties Yards and Store-houſes at <hi>Chatham, Deptford, Woolwich,</hi> and <hi>Portsmouth;</hi> the want where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, doth at preſent Rob one Yard to Supply another, after the Proviſion taken thence was laid in there at exceſſive Rates and Prizes, and after the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of Land, and Water-Carriage, Cranage, Portage, Labourers Wages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to Lodge them for his Majeſties Service in that Yard, which (as before I hinted) is no ſmall Devourer of his Majeſties Treaſure, and conſequently a begetter of his Debts, beſides the Diſſervice that is done to his Majeſty, when the Service in that Yard ſhall call for the Uſe of the ſame Proviſions.</p>
            <p>In ſhort the Way Propoſed, will (if I miſtake not) be effectual in a ſhort time, not only to bring his Majeſty out of Debt, but alſo to prevent his being in Debt for the Future, by cutting off all Eating Charges upon his Majeſties Treaſure whatſoever, if the Aides already ſetled upon him, be found upon their full Improvement, to be ſufficient to carry on his Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with Honour, and if not, yet to ſatisfie the Parliament ſo as to Give and Grant him ſuch further Aides, as may and will do it Effectually, without any Application to private Men, by the preſent forenamed Contrivances, and Practices, which are ſo far from anſwering the End Propoſed by them, that they are the Foundations of thoſe great Debts that are Incumbent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and never will, nor indeed can free him from them, but plunge and involve him deeper and deeper in them, the longer they are continued by him.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
